Guide to the Society of the 9019 records, 1892-1943
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Society of the 9019 records 1892-1943
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. The Society of the 9019.
5.5 Linear Feet 2500 Items
The Society of 9019, organized in February 1890 under the leadership of John Spencer Bassett, was an honorary scholarship fraternity. The society began at Trinity College and continued on at Duke University. Acceptance into the 9019 was based, in part, on an academic average of 90 or above. It was also conditioned upon a scholastic average of 2.25 quality points, making it similar to the male only Phi Beta Kappa society. The 9019 is credited with establishing the South Atlantic Quarterly, supporting scholarly activities among North Carolina high schools, and establishing student-faculty forums on a variety of timely subjects. The group disbanded in the early 1940s.
The 9019 records contain ritual and member lists, program and contest advertisements, ceremonial robes, founding documents, letters, photographs, memorabilia and other papers related to this honor society. The dates of the materials range from 1892-1944.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Society of the 9019 records were received by the University Archives as a transfer from Mrs Mattie Erma E. Parker in 1978.
Historical Note
The Society of the 9019 was the first honor society at Trinity College. In February of 1890, John Spencer Bassett founded the Society of the 9019 and became its first president. Bassett’s desire to arouse the intellectual and literary interests of students and to stimulate interest in the history of the South inspired him to create the 9019. The 9019 recognized the outstanding students of the college, encouraged its members to promote scholarship on campus and in the community, and fostered a "true college spirit." The origin of the name is a representation of a) the 90 percent average required for admittance and b) the number of original members. As a precursor to Phi Beta Kappa, the 9019 provided a unique opportunity for recognition and involvement in campus activities. Notable contributions include the creation of the South Atlantic Quarterly and supporting scholarly activities among North Carolina high schools via annual declamation contests. The 9019 continued operation throughout the transformation to Duke University, but competing fraternities and World War II brought an end to the organization.
Collection Overview
The 9019 records contain ritual and member lists, program and contest advertisements, ceremonial robes, founding documents, letters, photographs, memorabilia and other papers related to this honor society. Major subjects include: intellectual life; student societies; initiations and rites and ceremonies; oratory competitions, and the South Atlantic Quarterly. The dates of the materials range from 1892-1944.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
United States -- Intellectual life.
United States -- Intellectual life -- 19th century.
United States -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.
Duke University -- Societies, etc.
Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.
Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.) Duke University -- History.
John Spencer Bassett, 1867-1928.
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)
Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.)
Rites and ceremonies.
Oratory -- Competitions -- North Carolina.
South Atlantic Quarterly.
Honor Societies.
The 9019.
Related Material
University Archives Photograph Collection, 1861-2006
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 6 Boxes
  - Letters 1892-1910 (payments for various services) (Box 1)
  - Letters 1911-1917 (letters of recommendation from high school administrators declamation contests)
  - Letters 1922-1928
  - Letters 1929-1936
  - 1930; Alumni; spring initiation, 40th year anniversary celebration planning; photographs
  - Letters regarding the 9019 Interscholastic Declamation Contest 1910-1919
  - Advertisements and official programs for various declamation contests from 1910-1929
  - Articles of incorporation, constitution, and minutes Book – A bound notebook containing names and addresses of members (not a complete listing); certificates of initiation for the years 1939. Memorabilia
  - 1936 clipping (transferred from the W.H. Pegram Papers to the 9019 Collection). The folder is labeled: “Clipping, 1936) – There is a photo of and caption about the charter members of the 9019. (Box 2)
  - Contains a 1939 certificate of initiation in the 9019 (there are others in box 1)
  - Book – Minutes 1919-1934
  - Loose papers – Origin of the name 9019; John Spencer Bassett (founder) memorial charter; declamation contest papers.
  - Eugene S. Edwards papers on the 9019. 1892-1904.
  - Printed materials, flyers, etc.
  - The 9019 and the South Atlantic Quarterly
  - Various literary writings (fragile); probably subject matter for declamation contests and discussion amongst the members.
  - The Pearl Speaker, a source-book for orations. (Box 3)
  - Minute book 1916-1918.
  - Treasurer’s records bound together by rope; two notebooks and one folder with 9019 financial records.
  - The membership list is arranged by graduating class on a stack of index cards. (Box 4)
  - Folders containing printed membership lists
  - Folders containing printed ritual procedures
  - A ceremonial initiation ritual notebook
  - Contains ceremonial robes (Box 5)
  - Contains ceremonial robes (Box 6)